Digital Tale of Genji - Feature Introduction.
デジタル源氏物語、機能紹介。
We will explain the AI Image Search.
AI画像検索についてご説明します。
AI Image Search cross-searches manuscript images based on the Koigenji Monogatari,
AI画像検索とは、校異源氏物語を基準に、
finding pages with high text similarity across multiple manuscripts and printed editions.
類似度の高い写本・版本の画像を横断検索する機能です。
It is useful for finding image data of specific scenes in the Tale of Genji.
源氏物語の特定場面の画像データを探すのに便利です。
The registration status shows searchable manuscripts and editions listed by chapter.
登録状況では、検索対象の写本・版本を帖単位で一覧できます。
Let us explain how similarity is calculated.
類似度の算出方法についてご説明します。
First, text data is attached to each image using kuzushiji OCR.
まず、源氏物語の各画像データにくずし字OCRでテキストデータを付与します。
Then, the text data is compared with the Koigenji Monogatari at the double-page spread level.
次に、そのテキストデータと校異源氏物語を見開きページ単位で比較します。
Results are displayed in order of highest similarity.
類似度の高いものから順に表示されます。
Here is how to access the search screen.
検索画面へのアクセス方法です。
Access it from "AI Image Search Edition" in the menu.
メニュー画面の「AI画像検索版」からアクセスします。
Click the menu item on the left side.
左側のメニューをクリックしてください。
Click the search button.
検索ボタンをクリックします。
We will explain the search workflow.
検索の流れをご説明します。
Here are the steps to find image data of a specific scene.
特定場面の画像データを探すまでの手順です。
Step 1: Find the page in the Koigenji Monogatari that corresponds to the scene.
ステップ1：場面に該当する校異源氏物語のページを探します。
Step 2: Select manuscript pages with high similarity.
ステップ2：類似度の高い写本・版本のページを選びます。
Step 3: Compare with the Koigenji Monogatari to confirm the correct page.
ステップ3：校異源氏物語と写本・版本を比較して該当ページか確認します。
Let us start with Step 1.
まずステップ1です。
Search the text of the Koigenji Monogatari.
校異源氏物語の本文を検索します。
Enter a word from the scene. For example, "inuki."
場面に含まれる語句を入力します。例えば「いぬき」。
You can narrow results by specifying a chapter.
巻を指定して検索を絞り込むこともできます。
Search results are displayed.
検索結果が表示されます。
The Koigenji Monogatari image and text are shown.
校異源氏物語の画像と本文テキストが表示されます。
Confirm whether this is the page of the scene you are looking for.
探している場面のページか確認してください。
Here are some search tips.
検索のコツです。
Searches using different notation from the Koigenji Monogatari text will not produce hits.
校異源氏物語の表記と異なる検索ではヒットしません。
For example, searching "犬君" in kanji won't work; use "いぬき" in hiragana instead.
例えば「犬君」では検索できず、「いぬき」で検索する必要があります。
Try switching between kanji and kana, with or without voiced marks.
漢字・かなの違い、濁点の有無、踊り字などを試してみてください。
Now, Step 2.
ステップ2に進みます。
Select manuscript pages with high similarity scores.
類似度の高い写本・版本のページを選びます。
Select the manuscript pages to compare.
写本・版本のページを選択します。
The similarity calculation results are displayed.
類似度の計算結果が表示されます。
Items colored yellow are pages included in the Koigenji Monogatari.
黄色で着色されたものは校異源氏物語に含まれるページです。
Traffic light icons indicate secondary use conditions.
信号機アイコンは二次利用条件を示しています。
The Todai manuscript shows candidates at 46% and 41% similarity.
東京大学本は類似度46%と41%の候補が表示されています。
Candidates from the University of Tokyo Faculty of Letters collection are also shown.
東京大学文学部所蔵本の候補も表示されます。
Manuscript images are loading.
写本の画像が読み込まれます。
Similarity scores are displayed for each manuscript.
各写本の類似度が表示されています。
Secondary use condition icons can also be confirmed.
二次利用条件のアイコンも確認できます。
Manuscripts from Tsukuba University and the Imperial Household Agency are also shown.
筑波大学所蔵本や宮内庁書陵部所蔵本も表示されます。
Images of the Koigenji Monogatari page and high-similarity pages are displayed.
校異源氏物語の該当ページと類似度の高いページの画像が表示されます。
You can compare manuscripts from different collections.
各所蔵先の写本を比較できます。
Click a page number to display the manuscript image.
ページ番号をクリックすると、写本・版本の画像が表示されます。
Now, Step 3.
ステップ3に進みます。
Compare with the Koigenji Monogatari to confirm the correct page.
校異源氏物語と写本・版本を比較して、該当するページか確認します。
It can be difficult to confirm content from images alone.
写本の画像だけでは内容の確認が難しいこともあります。
Comparing the body text is recommended.
本文テキストを比較して確認するのがおすすめです。
Select "Compare by Text."
「テキストで比較する」を選択します。
Click "String Similarity Comparison."
「文字列の類似度比較」をクリックします。
The comparison tool is loading.
比較ツールが読み込まれます。
The text comparison tool is now displayed.
テキスト比較ツールが表示されました。
Koigenji Monogatari text on the left, selected image text on the right.
左側に校異源氏物語のテキスト、右側に選択画像のテキストが表示されます。
Comparison results are shown in the center.
中央に比較結果が表示されます。
Continuing with text comparison.
テキストで比較する方法の続きです。
The "Image" tab shows the Koigenji Monogatari and manuscript images side by side.
「画像」タブで、校異源氏物語と写本の画像を並べて確認できます。
The "Text (Diff)" tab shows text differences.
「テキスト（差分）」タブで、テキストの差分を確認できます。
Blue lines indicate corresponding sections between the texts.
差分が青い線で対応箇所を示しています。
Here are some additional features.
その他の機能をご紹介します。
Links to related materials.
関連資料へのリンク機能です。
A link to the Koigenji Monogatari at the National Diet Library.
校異源氏物語（国立国会図書館）へのリンクがあります。
A link to the Shinpen Nihon Koten Bungaku Zenshu on JapanKnowledge.
新編日本古典文学全集（ジャパンナレッジ）へのリンクもあります。
The Koigenji Monogatari text viewer is displayed.
校異源氏物語のテキストビューアが表示されます。
The corresponding page in the National Diet Library Digital Collection opens.
国立国会図書館デジタルコレクションの該当ページが開きます。
A scanned image of the Koigenji Monogatari is displayed.
校異源氏物語のスキャン画像が表示されます。
The link to the Shinpen Nihon Koten Bungaku Zenshu is also available.
新編日本古典文学全集へのリンクも利用できます。
You can view the corresponding section on JapanKnowledge Lib.
ジャパンナレッジLibで該当箇所を閲覧できます。
Here is how to check secondary use conditions.
二次利用条件の確認方法です。
Traffic light icons indicate the conditions.
信号機アイコンで二次利用条件を示しています。
Green means free use, yellow means conditional, red means application required.
緑は自由利用可能、黄色は条件あり、赤は要申請です。
About the heart button.
ハートボタンについてです。
Click it when the result matches what you are looking for.
お探しのものと一致していたらクリックしてください。
The number of hearts serves as a guide to similarity.
ハートの数が類似度の目安になります。
Login is required to use this feature.
利用するにはログインが必要です。
Please check the privacy policy for handling of authentication information.
認証情報の取り扱いはプライバシーポリシーをご確認ください。
Digital Tale of Genji.
デジタル源氏物語。
Thank you for watching.
Digital Tale of Genji。